<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuels funerall. Or A sermon preached at the funerall of Sir Anthonie Cope Knight, and Barronnet. By Mr. Robert Harrice</title>
            <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02715</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103801</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839546</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839546</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3977</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02715)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3977)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1025:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Samuels funerall. Or A sermon preached at the funerall of Sir Anthonie Cope Knight, and Barronnet. By Mr. Robert Harrice</title>
                  <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Felix Kyngston for Thomas Man, and are to be sold at the signe of the Talbot in Pater-noster row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On 1 Samuel XXV, 1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cope, Anthony, --  Sir, 1548 or 9-1615 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3977:1"/>
            <p>SAMVELS FVNERALL. <hi>OR</hi> A SERMON PREACH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED AT THE FVNERALL of Sir ANTHONIE COPE Knight, and Barronnet.</p>
            <p>BY M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ROBERT HARRICE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALME 37. verſ. 37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Marke the perfect man, and behold the vpright, for the end of that man is peace.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Felix Kyngston</hi> for <hi>Thomas Man,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Talbot in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-noſter row. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3977:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3977:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE LADIE ANNE COPE, LATE WIFE to Sir <hi>A. C.</hi> Knight, and Barrennet <hi>at Brewdene, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM,</hi> Your right is greateſt to this Sermon, as being heire to the man, though not to his lands: what he was, I neede not tell your Ladiſhip; nor will I ſay of you as once one ſaid of a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Ladie: I know not, <note place="margin">Hic haeres vxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris at haeredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis alij poſſeſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Hiero. of Pammach. and Paulina. Valer. of Cornelia; Neſeis an faeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorem dixerim, quòd talem vir<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> habuerit, an miſeriorem quòd amiſerit. l.4. Nec doleas quòd talem amiſeris, ſed gaudeas quòd talem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bueris. Ier. to Heliodor. for his nephew.</note> whether your vnhappineſſe be greater in now looſing him, then was your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in once enioying him. A Chriſtian may be happy in loſſes and croſſes, as well as otherwhere; and wee in Chriſts ſchoole muſt learne with <hi>Iob,</hi> to bleſſe God for friends paſt, as well as preſent; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praiſe him for once lending them, then ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieue for his calling for them againe. The time will be better ſpent, if (leauing theſe impertinencies) I call vpon your Ladiſhip, and my ſelfe, for ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouement of this croſſe: and firſt (Madame) let vs obſerue the crookednes of our nature, which neither feares croſſes till it feeles them, nor ſees mercies till they are out of ſight; it being with the ſoule as with the eye, that ſees nothing that is not ſomwhat diſtant
<pb facs="tcp:3977:3"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. Next, be pleaſed (I pray) to conſider the vanity of this world, what is now leſt of your Honourable husband more then his goodnes? Where is health, where is beauty, where is honour now? In how ſhort a ſpace were two of the chiefeſt flowers in the <hi>Copes</hi> garden withered? Ah (Madame) it is grace, it is grace and wiſedome that will cauſe our face to ſhine, and name to liue: as for the glory of this world, it is like a rotten poſt, that ſhines indeed, but it is onely in the darke; neuer build vpon it, for all its gliſtering, it is but a rotten poſt. Thirdly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member we (I beſeech you) our owne eſtate: indeed it were much if we ſhould forget death, <note place="margin">Salus corporis, patrimonium pauperis. <hi>Aug. in Pſal. 76.</hi>
               </note> who are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue halfe dead. For mine owne part, the Lord hath already ſtript me of the poore mans portion, health: for your Ladiſhips, a great part of your ſelfe is now turned into duſt, ſeeing pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, husbands are gone before you, and death hath come very neare you, when thrice it hath cut off your head; the time will ſhortly come when you alſo muſt yeeld to the ſtroke of death. In the meane, I beſeech you remember <hi>S. Iohns</hi> words, in an Epiſtle to another Ladie, Looke to your ſelfe, that wee loſe not thoſe things which wee haue wrought, but that wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a full reward: indeed your loſſe will bee ours too (for wee expect a tithe in heauen of our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encreaſe, as well as heere): and therefore (good Madame) husband your ſoule well, ſowe much, worke much, giue much, pray much, and you and wee ſhall ſpeed the better at that harueſt. Thus praying your fauourable conſtruction and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of theſe rude lines, with humble thanks for all
<pb facs="tcp:3977:3"/>your loue to mee, (eſpecially to thoſe many poore members of Chriſt, to whom it pleaſeth you (thorough my hands) to conuey yeerely ſo great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe) I commend you to the Lords grace; who abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly returne all that comfort vpon you, which you haue ſo frankly yeelded to ſo many naked backes, and hungry bellies in this Church. From <hi>Hanwell,</hi> Iuly 11. the ſame day whereon (foure yeeres before) your worthy husband was there interred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Ladiſhips in all Chriſtian ſervices,</hi> RODERY HARRICE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3977:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3977:4"/>
            <head>TO THE GODLY READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon, at it was neuer meant to the Preſſe, ſo bath it been kept from it almost foure yeeres: Now it is conſtrained to ſhew it ſelfe, as ſometimes Trinces bee, leſt ſome counterfeit ſteale their name, and vſurpe their place. Whileſt <hi>Samuels</hi> body ſlept, the <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>So Auſten</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim; immundus ſpiritus, malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſpiritus.</note> diuell would be <hi>Samuel,</hi> &amp; deceine with <note n="b" place="margin">Image Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elis, ſumilitudo Sam, imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſimulatio Samuel, &amp;c. <hi>ſo others</hi> v. D. Rayn. leſt.</note> ſhewes, I had reaſon to feare ſome ſuch like ingling with <hi>Samuels</hi> funerall, being fore-threatned. In this extremity, if I had rather my owne child beare my name then a baſtard, blame mee not. Now thou ſeeſt it, take me with thee a little, before thou readeſt it: Know, that the firſt point onely was enlarged, the reſt thus briefly (as thou findeſt them) touched by reaſon of haſt, being tyed to an houre. Secondly, know, that I neuer wrote forth theſe notes but once, and that is the reaſon of the moſt of the marginall quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and references, it being now my ordinary practice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre my ſelfe in priuate notes to ſuch Authors, as haue written (within my memory and reading) of the ſame ſubiect, although in publike I quote ſparingly. Thirdly, vnderſtand the true reaſon of my forbearing perſonall praiſes in the cloſe: my text gaue me occaſion of ſaying ſomthing before, &amp; me thought it handſomer to lay al my ſtuffe vpon the foundation, then to ſet vp a leane-to. Secondly, I remembred what a wiſe man ſaid, <note place="margin">Sapientia non quaerit vocis teſtimon um, ſed operum. Hierod. in Math. lib. 2.</note> Wiſdome grounds vpon mens workes, rather then words. Thirdly and eſpecially, I finde the practice (though in it ſelfe lawful) exceedingly abuſed, I haue no leiſure now to take vp the complaints of worthy Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters againſt this abuſe; onely I could wiſh, that our age would diſtinguiſh betwixt funerall Orations, and funerall Sermons, as former ages haue done, and not confound ſo different things. It is fit that grace ſhould be followed euen to heauen with honour:
<pb facs="tcp:3977:5"/>but oh that euery of Chriſts meſſengers would remember his maſter, and before he ſpeakes, aske himſelfe the queſtion; Would my Lord and maſter ſpeake this himſelfe, were he now to preach in perſon? but I must not dwell in the porch. One thing more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I leaue thee, thou ſeest the guiſe of this world, Printers get copies for their profit; Readers buy and reade for their pleaſure, and (perhaps) ſome print too for their credit: but where is the man that proiects his owne ſpirituall good? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily the number of ſuch is ſmall, be thou of that number, make ſome vſe of others liues, of others deaths, trifle not as many doe: what is this ſame <hi>R. H.</hi> &amp;c? who was this <hi>A. C.</hi> a good or a bad man, &amp;c? bee thou godly, and I care not what thou eſteemest of me: as for this worthie Gentleman in ſpeech, vnderſtand, that as I neuer flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him liuing; ſo will I not deifie him (as the Heathen did their Patrones) being dead. <note place="margin">Herodian.</note> He had his wants, his faults, nor did wee concurre in all opinions: but I would that thou and I, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially men of his owne rank would follow him in theſe particulars: first, in praying most earneſtly, and particularly againſt our ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſinnes; ſecondly, in louing and reuerencing our own teachers; and that ſo much the more, by how much the more frecly and plainly they reprone vs. For theſe things (not to ſpeake of other particulars) much commend the truth of that Honourable Knight, that in his ſtanding prayers with his family, hee would ſhame himſelfe moſt in his confeſſions for his owne moſt ſpeciall ſinnes. And againe, as he much reſpected, and greatly countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced euery learned and vnſcandalous Preacher: ſo most of all thoſe that leaſt fauoured his corruptions; often bleſſing God for ſuch teachers as would not giue him rest in ſinne, and not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prouoking them, at leaſt my ſelfe (to ſpeake of my owne knowledge onely) with ſuch like words: <hi>Goe on, ſpare vs not; though corruption may buſle a while, yet God will giue vs hearts to come in at length, and to ſubmit to the ſcepter of his Word; howſoeuer, it ſhall bee a Preachers Crowne to be faithfull, and to baulke none.</hi> Thus bee many a time to mee in priuate, after that I had been (as the world thought) ſharpe enough with him in publike. Oh that we had more ſuch Knights, ſuch hearers now! But I forget my ſelfe to remember thee of a dutie, Shall I ſay on: thing more in his bonour? The Papists
<pb facs="tcp:3977:5"/>neuer loued him; and therefore if they in thy hearing now perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his name, ſay as a Father once ſaid of a cruell perſecuter, That religion which they ſo perſecute, must needs be excellent: This I can aſſure thee, his end was moſt comfortable, and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour no way obſcured, nor his memorie loſt in his owne country by death. More then this I haue not now to ſay to thee, onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that thou haſt gotten one more witneſſe againſt thee in the last day, by reading this Sermon, vnleſſe thou put it to ſome vſe. Farewell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thine in the Lord, R. H.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3977:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3977:6"/>
            <head>SAMVELS FV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERALL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. SAMVEL, 25.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And Samuel dyed, and all the Iſraelites were gathered together, and lamented him, and buried him in his houſe at Ramah. And Dauid aroſe, and went downe to the wilderneſſe of Paran.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y this time you ſee the ſumme of our now errand and preſent text: the worke in hand is a funerall, the partie deceaſed worthy <hi>Samuel;</hi> the mourners, all Iſrael; the place of buriall, his owne houſe at <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah.</hi> The whole paſſage penned, either by <hi>Gad,</hi> or <hi>Nathan</hi> (as it ſhould ſeeme by the Chronicles) at Gods appointment; whoſe eye followes euery mourner here, and therefore it behoues vs to follow his voyce with our beſt attentions. For my owne part, I am very ſenſible of the difficulties I now ſuſtaine: for the ſubiect of our diſcourſe, <hi>Samuels</hi> funerall is enough to aſtoniſh any Iſraelite; for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is not eaſie to ſay, what will be moſt expediently ſaid; and for manner wee haue things, almoſt incompatible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile, plaineneſſe and briefeneſſe in the ſame ſpeech: the text giues ſome aduantage by its plaineneſſe and fulneſſe, yeelding matter of large vſe from three ſorts of men of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt qualitie; from <hi>Samuel</hi> dying, from <hi>Iſrael</hi> mourning, from
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3977:7"/>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> flying; of all whom, whileſt I ſpeake plainely, doe you heare conſcionably, ſo God ſhall haue his end, and I my aime.</p>
            <p>And firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> he dies; the time is geſſed at by men, but not expreſſed by God: ſome knit this ſtory with that next before, becauſe of the word <hi>(And),</hi> but that particle in the original, is ſometimes ordinatiue, as wel as copulatiue, and begins ſometimes a new ſtorie, a new book ſometimes. <hi>'Paul</hi> is moſt expreſſe for the time, <note place="margin">Exod. 1.1. Ezek<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 1. P<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Mont. in <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> V<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>enda<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mp. Sa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>who g<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> him a longer time,</hi> H<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cus <hi>yet more,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>and</hi> I<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>allus <hi>moſt of all. 1.</hi> Sam. 3 20.2. Sam 12.</note> Act. 12; where ſumming vp the reigne of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> he makes the whole 40 yeeres, whereof not much aboue two or three (if I miſtake not, falls to <hi>Saul,</hi> the other are <hi>Samuels,</hi> ſo ancient a Ruler as this worthie, yet now he dies: what further he was we need not ſay, his name and ſtorie ſpeakes it ſufficiently, he was begged of God, borne of honeſt parents, brought vp in beſt faſhion, aduanced to higheſt emploiments in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale; a Prophet approued of God and man a Magiſtrate to whom heauen and earth in the day of his reſignation gaue applauſe; God ſpake from heauen in his voice of thunder, man could not vpon the ſharpeſt challenge charge him with any indirectneſſe in gouernment; this <hi>Samuel</hi> ſo well deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo much regarded, ſo holy in life, ſo high in place, a good Chriſtian, a good Church-man, a good Sates-man, now dies and yeelds to nature.</p>
            <p>In his death lets reade our owne, and grow to this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Death is vnauoydable, life and death take turnes each of other; the man liues not that ſhall not ſee death, be he a King with <hi>Saul,</hi> a Prophet with <hi>Ieremie,</hi> a wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi> a fooliſh <hi>Nabal,</hi> a holy <hi>Iſaac,</hi> a prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> of what ſort ſoeuer, hee muſt be deaths priſoner; nay, let there bee a concurence of all in one, let <hi>Samuel</hi> be both a good man, and a good Miniſter, and a good Magiſtrate, and haue as many priuiledge, as are incident to a man yet can he not procure a protection againſt this officer; his mother may beg his life, but none can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound for his death. Speake we this according to men? ſaith not the Scripture as much? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.10.</note> Wiſe men die (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) and fooles die; rich men die, and poore to; and therfore he cals both vpon the ſonnes of Nobles, and of the earth to mind
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3977:7"/>the leſſon: indeed the Heathens could compare the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> to Counters, Cheſſe, Stage-playes; in reckoning Counters haue their ſeuerall place and vſe for a time, but in the end they are all iumbled on a heape; in a game at Cheſſe, ſo ne are Kings, ſome Biſhops, &amp;c, but after a while they go all into the ſame bagge: on the Stage, one is in his raggs, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in his robes; one is the Maſter another the Man, and very buſie they bee, but in the end the Play ends, the braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ends, and each returnes to his place; ſuch (and no other) is the eſtate of man, euen in their iudgement, al are either weeds or flowers, both wither; all trees good or bad, both die; as dieth the foole, ſo the wiſe, ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. In the manner there is ſome difference, for the matter none; but why doe I proue what none denies? Both liuing and dead giue teſtimonie to this truth; the liuing may take vp <hi>Iobs</hi> words in another caſe; We are filled with wrinckles, which is a witneſſe againſt vs, wee weare death in our faces, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 16.8.</note> and beare it in our bones, we put it vpon our backes, and into our mouthes, and cannot bee ignorant of it. Yea, the dead pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime this leſſon, and in this reſpect (like <hi>Abell</hi>) are liuing Prophets, when dead men; Goe to the Word, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4.</note> goe to the earth; and they that make their beds in darkeneſſe, and ſleepe in the duſt will tell you, that its neither wiſdome, nor power, nor ſtrength, nor friends, nor place, nor grace, nor any thing elſe that can exempt from this tribute of nature (Death), as darkeneſſe could call it: our <hi>Abel</hi> here dead ſpeakes this to all his friends; If greatneſſe of eſtate, feature of body, gifts of mind, chaſtenes of life, ſobernes in diet, diligence in a calling, prayers of the Church, would haue giuen any aduantage againſt death, darkeneſſe and blackneſſe had not at this time couered vs: ſith the ſtrong is become weake, let vs with <hi>Sampſon</hi> out of the ſtrong gather meate; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> and ſee firſt whence this is, and next how it may be improued for vſe, that there is no preſcription againſt death. For the firſt, the holy Ghoſt referres vs to a threefold reaſon of mans mortalitie, each of which hath place in all men, as well as any. The firſt of which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is taken from the decree of God, its a ſtatute enacted in that higheſt Court, the voyce of heauen, that man ſhould once
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3977:8"/>die: this ſtatute we reade in <hi>Pauls</hi> ninth to his Hebrews, and in the entrance into Gods booke; which as it was laid vpon mankind in <hi>Adams,</hi> ſo hath it euer hitherto, and ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for euermore lay hold on his poſteritie. No man as yet hath breathed, but he hath had his death or tranſlation: no man is yet to come, but he muſt ſee either death, or an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo hath heauen concluded it, and who can poſſibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe it?</p>
            <p>The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſecond is taken from the matter whereof all men are made; the Scripture compares man to a houſe, whoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is laied in the duſt, whoſe walles are made of clay, the whole is but a tabernacle, and that of earth, and that of mans building, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 19. &amp; 10 9 &amp; 13.12. &amp;c.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> (after <hi>Iob</hi>) tels vs: this is the eſtate of man, of all men; ſome are more painted then ſome, but all earthen veſſels; ſome more cleare then ſome, but all glaſſes; all built of earth, all borne of women, and therefore all ſhort of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.</note> as <hi>Iob</hi> inferres.</p>
            <p>The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> third is taken from the proper cauſe of death, <hi>Sinne:</hi> ſinne is poyſon to the ſpirits, rottennes to the bones where it comes; and where doth it not come? who can ſay, his heart is cleane? <note place="margin">1 <hi>Epiſt chap.</hi> 1. <hi>veſ.</hi> 8.10.</note> Nay, who can waſh either heart or hand? <hi>Iohn</hi> anſwers the queſtion negatiuely, no man can acquit himſelfe from ſinne (if growne) either actuall or originall; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not from death. Shall wee then ſumme vp all, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all vnder death with the ſame breath: thus it ſtands; It is impoſſible for any liuing wight to fruſtrate the voyce and ſentence of God, to be a man or earth, and not to haue a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of earth; to be borne of the vncleane, and not to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane; therefore its impoſſible for him to auoide death. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed had Chriſt vndertaken our freedome from all deaths, as well as from ſome; or were there any power, counſell, &amp;c, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord; or could any place priuiledge any from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne of women, or made of duſt, or tainted with ſinne, then ſuch might conteſt with death, and impleade corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but ſith the former is impoſſible, the latter muſt be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnauoidable. And the<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore now what's to be done?</p>
            <p>Surely as men that muſt trauell, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſes. </seg>
               </label> ſtand not to diſpute, but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> arme themſelues for all weather: ſo muſt we; die wee muſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3977:8"/>that's alreadie concluded; young and old, good and bad, &amp;c. Whatſoeuer wee bee now, wee muſt bee dead anon, ſo ſaith God; let vs ſay the ſame, and prepare for it; nay, let's not ſay it, but think it; nay, not think it, but conclude it with greateſt affirmations: you will thinke ſtrange (perhaps) my paines in this kind, whileſt I perſwade a mortalitie; but the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is both needfull and vſefull; needfull in regard of our inſufficiencie to aſſume, and vnwillingneſſe to apprehend death in our ſelues: for howſoeuer wee can all ſay in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, we are mortall, nothing ſo ſuer as death; yet when it comes to our owne particular, we dreame of an immortalitie in nature, we neuer ſet any bounds to life, we do not reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude, I muſt die ſhortly, I may inſtantly, this day may be the laſt that I ſhall ſee, this hower the laſt that I ſhal ſpend, this word the laſt that I ſhall ſpeake, this deed the laſt that I ſhall performe, this place the laſt that I ſhall breathe in; and ſo liue by the day, by the hower: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we enter the how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the eldeſt of vs thinks to end it, nay the day, nay the week, nay the yere. Hence the moſt haue a yeeres work to do, when they haue not an howers ſpace to liue; needefull then it is to force this meditation of death vpon our harts: and as needful, ſo moſt vſeful; this will mind vs of the wofulnes of ſin, which turnes ſtrength into weakeneſſe, beautie into aſhes, life into death, a breathing man into a liueleſſe carcaſſe; this will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs of the iuſtice and truth of God, who is ſo pure, that he cannot but threaten ſinne; ſo true, that all the world cannot ſhift his threats; this wil worke humilitie, when the goodlieſt man muſt be twice a childe, and runne in a round, beginning with the earth, and ending in the earth, being at laſt what he was at firſt, not able to dreſſe himſelfe, to feede himſelfe, to helpe himſelfe, or ſpeake for helpe; this (in a word) wil work repentance towards God, modeſtie towards man, diligence in our callings, patience vnder croſſes, watchfulneſſe in all places, moderation in all caſes; and therefore this, this muſt be thought vpon. Nor muſt our thoughts be (as moſt mens be) ſhort and ſudden, fleeting and vncertaine, but we muſt be daily in theſe contemplations; &amp; particularly, we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what it is to die, what goes before it, what comes with it,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3977:9"/>what followes vpon it: for firſt, before we come to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gate of death, we are to paſſe through a very ſtrait, long, heauie lane: <note place="margin">Amari<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ita quam mo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Amb. de bono mortis, cap. 7.</note> ſickneſſe firſt tameth vs, which many times is worſe then death it ſelfe, that renders vs vnfit for all religious ſeruices, prayer, repentance, &amp;c, as being a time not of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but of ſpending; that cleaues the head, and paines the heart, and wounds the ſpirits, and leaues vs ſo diſtreſſed, that meate is no meate, the bed no bed, light no light to vs; that makes vs catch at death for help: but alas, what help in death, if not fore-thought of?</p>
            <p>Oh the miſerie of a poore creature, that is ſo pained that he cannot liue; ſo vnprepared that he dares not die: he goes to bed, but cannot ſleepe; he taſtes his meate, but it will not downe; he ſhifts his roome, but not his paine; death (ſaith the conſcience) would end and amend all, wert thou prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for death; but to die before, were to looſe thoſe comforts one hath, and to fall vnder thoſe curſes that are vnſufferable, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> &amp;c. But as yet we are but in the way to death. After ſicknes hath for a time entertained vs with ſharpeſt conflicts, it deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers vs vp to death it ſelfe: then the armies of feare diſplay themſelues, and ſtabbe the vnprouided ſoule through his thickeſt ſhield; then two powerfull officers ſeize vpon a maimed man at once; death vpon the body, terrour vpon the ſoule; death hales much like <hi>Salomons</hi> officers, and the ſoule holds (as <hi>Ioab</hi> the altar, ſo ſhe) the body; <note place="margin">1. <hi>King</hi> 2.</note> loth they be to part, but death will rend them in twaine; the conſcience the whileſt that meditates feare, that quakes, that trembles: Whither am I going? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>So</hi> Adrian <hi>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Animula, vagula, blandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula, &amp;c.</note> where muſt I lodge this night? where ſhall I liue hereafter? Oh that I might liue! Oh that I might die! Oh that I might doe neither! and knowes not what to chuſe; meane while, what caſe is this man in, whileſt death thus rips him vp, and thruſts his hands into his bowels to pull out his heart. Ah beloued, wee may intimate ſomewhat of his miſerie; but it falles not within our thoughts to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what his feare, be, who hangs between life and death, earth and hell, thus forthwith ready to drop into flames at euery ſtroke of death, and to ſinke downe, downe, downe, till he be gone for euer. And yet this is not all: when I am
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3977:9"/>dead (ſaith the carnal wretch), all the world is done with me: he ſaith truth, al the world, and all the comforts of the world haue done with him indeed; he ſhal neuer laugh more, he ſhal neuer haue a monie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts eaſe more: but though the world hath done with him, yet God hath not done with him; he ſends for his ſoule, (hauing firſt taken order that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body be forth-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming) conuents that, and doomes that, &amp; caſts that from him with greateſt indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, into ſuch a place, ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, ſuch a condition, as would make the heauens ſweat, and the earth ſhrinke to heare it. Well then (beloued), ſith die wee muſt, ſith we muſt be ſicke, be in paine, in feare, in tentation whileſt here; ſith we muſt to iudgement when we go hence; ſith that is moſt true of death, which antiquitie hath faigned of the Wolfe and Baſiliske; if wee ſee death before it comes to ſee vs, we ſhall then preuent the ſting, and poyſon, and fierceneſſe of it; if it ſteale vpon vs vnſeene, it leaues vs dumbe, nay dead: bee wee entreated by all the mercies of God, as we would pleaſe him, and pleaſure our ſelues, to take into our thoughts the often meditation of death, and to make due preparation for the ſame. Tell thy heart euery day, when thou takeſt it alone, in the words of <hi>Iob, When a few yeeres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 16.22.</note> (or as the text runnes) <hi>when the yeres of number (which are allotted me, namely) are come, then I ſhall goe the way, whence I ſhall not returne:</hi> ſay with him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 17.1.</note> 
               <hi>the graue is ready for me,</hi> (indeed <hi>graues</hi>); I muſt die, I muſt from all theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, theſe pleaſures, theſe friends; I muſt anſwere for all theſe deeds, theſe words, theſe thoughts; I muſt bee aſhamed, caſt, curſed, damned, burned, plagued as long as God liues, if I prepare not: I ſhal be ſpared, ſaued, bleſt, crowned, and be as neere to God as a creature can be to his maker, if I doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, therefore I muſt; I muſt, I will prepare for death. This done without all delayes, as a man that is now dying (as well as he for whom the bell toles, though not happily ſo neere to death) ſet vpon two things: Firſt, ſet thy houſe in order, next, thy ſoule. For the firſt, thou haſt perſons and things to looke vnto: to begin with perſons; ſo liue with thy wife, being a husband; with thy ſeruants, being a maſter; with thy children, being a father: exerciſe ſuch wiſedome, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3977:10"/>faithfulneſſe, mercy, euery day, as thou wouldeſt doe, if thou knoweſt it to be the laſt day. And for things (marke me wel, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ken not to Satan who diſſwades all ſeaſonable willes, becauſe hee would adminiſter the goods, by being timely in this errand, thou ſhalt not ſhorten thy dayes; but hauing taken thy leaue of the world, ſhalt better attend on death. Things therefore vnlawfull, reſtore, (I ſay againe) reſtore. Things lawfull diſpoſe of, and as in a iourney (haſtie and vncertaine) wait the call. But what auailes it to ſet houſe in order, with <hi>Achitophel,</hi> and to forget ones ſelfe. In the ſecond place therefore. (nay in the firſt) looke to thy ſelfe, and ſith the places be but two, and they ſo different, go not to hell, ſo long as heauen may bee had: there is no man ſo forlornely wicked,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Baſil.</note> but if he repent, wee may warrant him heauen; if he will not, who can helpe him? But what muſt he doe? firſt, he muſt repent, that is, ſee his life and nature, confeſſe, mourne, hate ſinne, and leaue all in practice or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance. Secondly, he muſt beleeue, that is, acquaint him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the Word, and yeeld conſent vnto it, apply it to his owne particular, and dwell vpon it: hee muſt threaten himſelfe in euery threat, curſe himſelfe in euery curſe, bleſſe himſelfe in euery promiſe. Thirdly, he muſt die daily to ſinne and the world, he muſt liue daily in the conſtant practice of al duties, religious towards God, righteous towards man, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate in his place &amp; calling. And ſo if he doth (in truth &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, though in much weakneſſe) there is no heauen, if he go not to heauen: if he do not thus (out of a preſumption of mercy, of life, and I know not what), there is none in hell if he be not one. Vp then (my brethren) and foreſlow no time: now the wind ſerues, hoyſe vp ſaile, now is the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, make your prouiſion; now is the ſeeds-time, ſowe apace, as yet you haue all aduantages from grace and nature, Word, Sacrament, wit, memory, ſenſe, ſtrength, &amp;c. Now appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the opportunity, repent and be pardoned; beleeue and be ſaued; obey, and be for euer bleſſed: if any hath perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelfe otherwiſe, my ſoule ſhall weepe in ſecret for his deſtruction, which I know will be as certainly effected, as now it is plainly threatned. Be entreated then, let God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3977:10"/>entreat you, and once ouer-rule you: you muſt die, you muſt die but once; being once dead, you returne not to make a new preparation; doe that once well, which being once wel done, will make you men, nay more then men, then Angels for euer. And this is the vſe for our ſelues. A ſecond reſpects our friends.</p>
            <p>Muſt all die, is there no remedie? then muſt we haue pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in our friends departure: a common lot,<note place="margin">Ferre quam ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem patiuntur omnes, nemo it. cuſat. <hi>Senec.</hi>
               </note> no man ſhould ſhrug at, euen in the Poets iudgement: who quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels ſummer for ſome heate, or winter for ſome cold? a thorn for pricking, or a brier for ſcratching? who is angry that he is framed like other men, ſubiect to like hunger, like thirſt, like ſleepe? and why (I pra'y) ſhould not our friends reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble others in their death, as well as in their birth? we would not haue them haue more eyes or hands then others,<note place="margin">v. <hi>Greg. Nyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> ſynod. de dormientibus.</note> and why more dayes? what doe we make of life, what of death? ſurely to the godly, life is but a priſon, death is an aduantage. Say our friends were tied in priſon, would wee begrudge them liberty? ſay toſt on the ſeas, would you enuie them the hauen? ſay doubtfull in the skirmiſh, would you bee ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for their victorie? nay, ſay but beaten with a tempeſt, would you not wiſh them at home? Beleeue it, <hi>Brethren,</hi> this world is but a ſea, a priſon; this life a iourney, a warfare: if God hath preuented our wiſhes, ſhall he bee returned fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe? ſhall wee trouble the ayre with needleſſe cries, my husband, my husband, my father, my father, as if wee were the firſt widowes and Orphans in the world? no, let them mourne without hope, whoſe life and death is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope: as for Chriſtians, who die liuing, and liue dying, they looſe nothing by death but what may well bee ſpared, <hi>ſinne, and ſorrow;</hi> they meet with nothing in heauen worthy teares; they goe not from, but to their friends; not from, but to their home; not from, but to their ioyes; a change in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they haue, but to their gaine. For firſt, ſo ſoone as death arreſts them, the world is well amended with them, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſoule; howbeit the full accompliſhment of their happineſſe is reiourned to the laſt day, that day of refreſhing, that day of reioycing, that day of marriage, of ſolemnity:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3977:11"/>then a full, a bleſſed change ſhall euidence it ſelfe to the whole world: and this change, if wee ſpeake in generall, is onely in qualities (as all alterations be) not in ſubſtance, the mettall is the ſame, onely it is refined; the ſtuffe the ſame, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is trimmed; the body and ſoule the ſame, onely it is newly clothed. If we deſcend to particulars, the change will bee found to bee in theſe following: in body, ſoule, eſtate, place, company: for the body, that is ſtript of all ſinfull and naturall defects (the abortions of ſinne), and filled with all heauenly complements; of mortall, it becomes immortall; of corruptible, incorruptible; of naturall, ſpirituall, (that is, not needing naturall helpes or props; there is no vſe of meat, apparell, ſleepe, beds, ) of diſhonourable, glorious, like (in its meaſure) to the body of Chriſt which is the ſtandard. In ſhort, whatſoeuer might make to the annoying, blemiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſhonouring, diſquieting of the body, is remoued; whatſoeuer might make it amiable, actiue, honourable, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, comfortable, is added; the glory of the Sunne will be but darkneſſe to it. For the ſoule, that is firſt eaſed of all the rags and reliques of ſinne, deliuered of ignorance, pride, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, &amp;c:<note place="margin">Generally all whoſe obiects are either fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or euill.</note> deliuered next of all the conſequences of ſinne, griefes, guilts, feares, accuſations; yea, deliuered of all things, which may any way import an imperfect ſtate, though an vpright heart, as faith, repentance, hungring after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c: and then in a ſecond place, it is filled with the image of Ieſus Chriſt. Firſt, all the powers and faculties therof are perfected and aduanced aboue the ordinary ſtraine of nature: next, all thoſe veſſels are ſtuffed with knowledge, loue, and all things elſe that are there requiſite: and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but the ſoule is furniſhed with all the attendances of Chriſts image, euerlaſting ioy, perpetuall peace, a conſtant correſpondency and communion with God: and in briefe, whatſoeuer might offend, ſtaine, blemiſh, the ſoule is remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and whatſoeuer may enrich it, ennoble it, and make it bliſſefull, is (according to each mans meaſure) added; And thus of the perſon. The reſt we diſpatch with all ſpeed, for the eſtate thus; there ſhall be nothing that ſhall be wanting, that ſhall trouble, diſtract, or diſcontent; there ſhall bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3977:11"/>that the ſoule ſhall then deſire, but there it is. For the place thus: there ſhall bee nothing leſſe then what ſhall bee deſired, nothing more that can bee deſired: what it is, the Word no where (for ought I know) tels vs. The Church on earth is more tich the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gold, more precious then pearle, more bright then the Suaue, more glorious then the Moone;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Read.</hi> 21.22.</note> but what is there to be ſeene, <hi>Paul</hi> could not vtter; wee cannot conceiue: onely this we know, that none ſhall be euer weary of it, or willing to alter it. Laſtly, for the companie, there bee of three ſorts: firſt, Angels, who ſhall not then terrifie, but attend; the worſt and loweſt ſeruant there, ſhall bee as an Angell. 2. All the famous and godly men that euer liued:<note place="margin">Illic Apoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pro <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tarum &amp;c. <hi>Cypr. de mort. ad fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres.</hi>
               </note> there ſhall we meete with <hi>Adam, abraham,</hi> &amp;c: there ſhall we be acquainted with <hi>Dauid, Paul,</hi> &amp;c. 3. The bleſſed Trinity, there ſhall we ſee him who hath done and ſuffered ſo much for vs: him, whom the Fathers before, and ſince his incarnation ſo much longed to ſee, Ieſus Chriſt the bleſſed: all which conſidered and beleeued, what can wee leſſe doe then abandon all fruitleſſe and fleſhly teares for friends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted? what way are they gone, but the way of all fleſh? with whom doe they liue, but with <hi>Samuel,</hi> with God? where are they, but in better place and caſe, with better friends then euer before? In ſtead of carking, therefore doe two other things, firſt, whileſt friends bee preſent,<note place="margin">Our vulg<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſeldome <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for friends till gone.</note> doe the part of a friend in praying for them, in calling vpon them, and in fitting of them to death, that ſo thou maieſt haue peace in thy ſelfe, and hope of them in their departure: Elſe when thy conſcience ſhall ſay vnto thee, Wretched man, thy wife, thy child, thy charge is now dead, and (for ought thou knoweſt) in hell; if not, no thankes to thee, for thou waſt neuer the man that would call vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pray with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or mind them of their departures: when (I ſay) thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſhall thus greet thee, thou ſhalt not tell how to take it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, when they are gone to bed, and faſt aſleepe, awake them not with thy cries, but make ready to follow after, ſo the time ſhall be beſt redeemed, the loſſe and croſſe beſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, and Satan (who loues to fiſh in ſuch troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) moſt preuented; and ſo farre this vſe.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3977:12"/>
            <p> We will touch vpon a third as we paſſe, and that is this: muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we all die? then here is a cooler for the wicked, and comfort for the godly. The wicked holds all his comforts onely for tearme of life; death ends his wealth, his glorie, his peace, his ioy, his comforts, his contentments; all his portion is onely in this life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.</note> ſaith the Prophet; all the ſweet he hath, foregoeth death; after he hath a portion indeed, but it is a portion of fier and brimſtone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.</note> of ſtormes and tempeſts, of anguiſh and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, of ſhame and confuſion, of horror and amazement in a firy lake, from the preſence of God in the middeſt of curſed ſpirits. Thus death muſt needs be terrible to him, but as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to the godly; for it makes his croſſes as ſhort, as the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> others comforts; the wicked ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not promiſe to himſelfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of an howres length, nor may the godly threaten him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with croſſes of an howres continuance: death in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant turnes the ſinners glory into ſhame,<note place="margin">Anima abſolui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, corpus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluitur. Ab. de bono vit. e. c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> pleaſure into paine, comfort into confuſion; death in an inſtant eaſeth the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies body of all paine, his ſoule of all ſinne, his conſcience of al feares, and leaues him in an eſtate of perfect happineſſe. Let then the godly comfort himſelfe in thoſe thoughts, which kill the wicked, euen in thoughts of death; let him for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward troubles reſolue, that death will be to him (as <hi>Michal</hi> once to <hi>Dauid</hi>) a meane to rid him of the hands of ſorrow; ſo that afflictions ſhall meete with none other then <hi>Sauls</hi> meſſengers did, a dead trunke in ſtead of a liuing <hi>Dauid:</hi> let him comfort himſelfe in the thoughts of his owne death, as once <hi>Eſau</hi> in the thoughts of his fathers, <hi>The dayes of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>will ſhortly come, then I will ſlay my brother:</hi> but the day of refreſhing (let the Chriſtian ſay) wil ſhortly come, and then I will ſlay my enemies, pride, vnbeliefe, ſelfe-loue; yea, all corruptions, all tentations, all miſeries, which ſtand ſome aboue vs, ſome about vs, as the inſulting Philiſtimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Samſon,</hi> ſhall end with the ſame blow, and fall with the ſame clap with our ſelues: happie they whoſe miſerie is no longer then life; but woe be to the wicked, whoſe iolity ends when death enters, and whoſe torments ſuruiue death it ſelf, and ſo we leaue <hi>Samuel</hi> to his reſt.</p>
            <p>Well, <hi>Samuel</hi> is well himſelfe, but in what caſe doth hee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3977:12"/>leaue his poore neighbours at <hi>Ramah,</hi> that the Text now ſpeakes, and it is my trouble (yet better one then al troubled) that I muſt ſpeake it ſo briefly: <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>Iacobs</hi> iſſue, Gods people, all Iſrael, diſtributiuely taken, that is, of all forts ſome were gathered in great troopes, either by publike command, or of their owne voluntarie, or both waies; firſt to lament, according to the then cuſtome in moſt ſolemne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Samuels</hi> end, and their owne loſſe; and next (to honour him) at his buriall in his <hi>Ramah.</hi> Here you ſee we haue farre to goe, and little time to ſpend, the faſter I haſten, the more you will hearken, and then I runne: the points, which in a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage or two muſt be touched from this part, are two; the firſt is this, <hi>Samuel</hi> a publike and proſitable man dieth, Iſrael publikely mourneth: you ſee what followeth; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> Great and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like loſſes muſt bee entertained with great and publike ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes; ſorrow muſt be ſuited to the loſſe, as a garment to the bodie, a ſhoe to the foote; when the cauſe of griefe is great, the meaſure of griefe muſt bee anſwerable. This is one principle, when a good man and neighbour dies, there is cauſe of great ſorrow: this is another, the inference will ſoone follow, and reſult hence, and that is our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; Good men of publike vſe and place, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> ſhould neuer paſſe to the graue vnlamented; their death ſhould be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and be wailed. Shall we proue this? God complaines when it is not ſo, in <hi>Iſaiah, The righteous periſh,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57.1.</note> 
               <hi>and no man conſidereth it.</hi> Next the Church hath practiſed euer this: when <hi>Iacob</hi> died, hee was lamented; ſo <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> ſo <hi>Ioſiah;</hi> ſo <hi>Stephen.</hi> Thirdly, wicked men haue performed this for good men, as <hi>Ioaſh</hi> for <hi>Eliſha; O my Father, my Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Kings</hi> 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>the Chariots of Iſrael, and the Horſemen of the ſame.</hi> Fourthly, good men haue performed this for wicked men, when vſefull Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, as <hi>Dauid</hi> for <hi>Saul,</hi> 2. Sam. 1.19. Laſtly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1 19.</note> Laſtly, reaſon calls for it; we muſt mourne, in reſpect of the cauſe of ſuch mens deaths; not priuate, but publike ſinnes too. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> God neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads a State, a Countrie, but for ſome treaſon. If <hi>Samuel</hi> die, it is becauſe God is angrie with the people: the ſheepe be not thankfull nor fruitfull, therefore the ſhepheard is ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:3977:13"/>
            <p> Secondly, in reſpect of the conſequents; take away good men, and good Magiſtrates, and ſecret ſinners grow open deſperate; the State lies open as a field vnfenced; the godly ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, mourne with Iſrael, or hide themſelues with <hi>Dauid.</hi> The righteous is taken away from the euill to come, ſaith <hi>Iſaiah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 57.1.</note> ther's a ſtorme comming ſo ſoone as he is houſed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of the loſſe it ſelfe; righteous men in the time of peace are the pillars of a State, they vphold the Iland, ſaith <hi>Iob:</hi> In time of warre and peace the horſemen and Chariots of their Iſrael; like <hi>Salomons</hi> waiters, for ſafety and honour; as needeful in a State as the head in the body, a ſtake in a hedge.</p>
            <p>Now ſhould it be thus when vſefull perſons die? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> what then ſhall we ſay to theſe times, wherein men haue not put off pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie onely, but nature alſo? No maruell if the Prophet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine the righteous periſh, and no man conſidereth it in heart. The wife periſheth, and the husband doth not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it; the parents periſh, and the children do not conſider it; the children periſh, and parents do not conſider it; few ſuch brethren as <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Ionathan;</hi> ſuch husbands as <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſuch children as <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Blind <hi>Polydor</hi> could taxe this, <hi>de iuuen. l. 6. c. 9.</hi> in vs of England.</note> ſuch fathers as <hi>Iacob.</hi> Theſe long, and long felt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of their deareſt friends: but now one month is enough to weare out al thoughts of a brother, nay of a child, nay of a mother, nay of a wife; nay in the neareſt tyes, one in that ſpace may bee buried, a ſecond woed, a third married. Now when nature dies, ſhall we looke for any life of grace? When theſe ſo neere be forgotten, can we hope that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhal be remembred? The righteous ſaid I? nay his death is ſome mans life, they ſit like <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> and <hi>Haman</hi> drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when all Iſrael is lamenting;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſt.</hi> 3.15.</note> they ſhoote with Gath and Askelon, as in the day of harueſt; &amp; (like impure Philiſtimes) ſport themſelues with others miſeries. But ſtay your ſelues (prophane mockers) died <hi>Samuel</hi> like a foole (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Abner</hi>)? or is his death any aduantage to you? No, his death is his owne gaine, but your loſſe; his death tels you, that you muſt die; thoſe ſoules of yours muſt bee torne from your bodies, thoſe bodies of yours muſt be mangled by death, after death you muſt be iudged, after iudgement pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3977:13"/>a 1000 yeres; when that's done, then another, then ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and another, and another; ſo long as God liues, ſo long your plagues ſhall laſt. His death tels you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.</note> that you are left as Iſrael in <hi>Moſes</hi> abſence, naked. The righteous being remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, you lie open to all ſinnes, ſnares, tentations, ſorrowes, and haue none to caſe and helpe you by his prayers. Your ſecret ioy at his death ſhewes you to be ſecret hypocrites: for what true member can part with a fellow member, without ſome ſorrow? your reioycing at calamities, preſages your owne miſeries, as <hi>Salomon</hi> tels you; and therefore tremble, and mocke not; mourne and ieſt not; ſay (if not in loue to the righteous, yet) to your ſelues, My Father, my Father, the Chariots of Iſrael, and the horſemen of the ſame. But let vs affoard them a little mirth here, that haue none elſe-where; and for our ſelues, ſith God complaines, that the righteous periſh, and no man conſidereth his death, lets ſpend ſome thoughts vpon that point, That the righteous periſh, who ſeeth not? Nay alas who ſeeth it? The Lord hath been vpon <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vs theſe many yeeres, and comes not in fauour to weede out the worſt, but in diſpleaſure to gather the ripeſt; amongſt the ſonnes of Maieſlie, hee hath ſmitten at the chiefeſt; amongſt our Nobles he hath taken of the beſt. Come to the gent<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, and the beſt goe. Nay, what ſhall we inſtance any farther? Death hath been at the Court, in the Citie, in the Countrie, in the Vniuerſitie, in places of higheſt marke, of greateſt zeale, and hath fetcht away the beſt, of Princes the beſt, of Nobles the beſt, of Magiſtrates the beſt, of Captaines, of Scholars, of Chriſtians, of all ſorts (all moſt) the beſt; and ſhould not this be conſidered? But there is more then this, in the Egipt of this world; we haue hitherto found a Goſhen: hitherto in hardeſt preſſures, &amp; worſt meaſures <hi>Dauid</hi> could go to <hi>Samuel</hi> in <hi>Ramah,</hi> and there meete with good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and comfort: but now both <hi>Samuel</hi> himſelfe dies, and poore <hi>Dauid</hi> muſt flie. Shall I (beloued) ſpeake as the thing is? In the fall of one Cedar of Ramah wee haue loſt much ſhade and ſhelter; in the ſplitting of one veſſel of price (wherein we had all our intereſſes and aduentures) we are all looſers: what we haue loſt, we ſhall better ſee ſeuen yeeres
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3977:14"/>hence, then now: but looſers we are, all looſers; Wife, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Neighbours, Friends, Miniſter, People, all looſers; ſo that here that is verified, which was anciently vttered of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, in one we haue loſt many; a chaſte Husband, a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Father, a religious Magiſtrate, a kind Neighbour, a good Church-man, a good States-man; in few, a <hi>Samuel.</hi> Speake I this after the fleſh to pleaſe? No, I ſpeake it for vſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: I report my ſelfe to your hearts. You tell me that you haue a publike loſſe, your mouthes haue vttered it, your faces ſpeake it; my eares, and eyes haue receiued it from you: and if ſo, then ſee what followes; if we haue Iſraels loſſe, we muſt make Iſraels lamentation; if with them we haue loſt in one many, at once much, we muſt be much and many in bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling this loſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>th</hi> 1.20.</note> Is our caſe <hi>Naomies?</hi> ſay with <hi>Naomi,</hi> call me pleaſant no more, call me bitter, for God hath fed me with bitterneſſe, and witneſſed againſt me: by denying mee this comfort, he teſtifies my vnthankfulneſſe for it. Is our place <hi>Dauids?</hi> let vs take vp <hi>Dauids</hi> words with <hi>Dauids</hi> affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I am diſtreſſed for thee brother <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.26.</note> very pleaſant haſt thou been to me, thy loue to me was wonderfull, paſſing the loue of women. Are we as <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Saul, Iſaac</hi> to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bekah,</hi> ſonnes? Are we as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> to <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> Prophets? As <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Abner,</hi> Kinſmen? are we by any name intituled to this loſſe? mourne, then mourne, not as the infidell deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor bitterly as doth the froward; but ſoberly as did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> when <hi>Abners</hi> death put him to a faſt. As God in life, ſo let vs in death put a difference betwixt <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Iehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 12.18.</note> let the one be buried in ſilence without an, Ah my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Ah ſiſter, as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> deſcribes it in his 22. Chapter: but for the other, all Iſrael muſt mourne with an holy mourning. Let his deareſt yoke-fellow ſay, Ah mine vnthankefulneſſe and vnfruitfulneſſe. let children ſay, Ah our diſobedience and ſtubburneſſe! and ſeruants, Ah our idleneſſe and vntruſtines! and all, Ah our folly and frowardneſſe! Who could not ſee vertues through frailties, and corne through chaſſe, til we had loſt all. Theſe ſinnes of ours haue ſtript vs of a <hi>Samuel,</hi> and couered vs with darkeneſſe. He is gone, the arme and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is fallen from this our little body, the ſooner for our ſins;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3977:14"/>let vs ſee it, or elſe what abides vs. In the body what medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines cannot doe, cutting muſt; what that cannot, burning muſt, or elſe nothing, (ſaith the maſter of Phyſick).<note place="margin">Hippocrat.</note> It is ſo in the ſoule to, Oh that we could ſee it! In our friends ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes we haue been medicined, in priuate diſtreſſes launced, but in the loſſe of publike perſons the Lord proceeds to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. If theſe wounds vpon the very head of vs ſtrike vs not downe. What ſhall next bee ſmitten but our heart it ſelfe? Well, Iſrael laments, and he hath cauſe; what doe they next? that next we muſt heare.</p>
            <p>They burie him, and the place and manner bee obſerued. For the place, they bury him (at his houſe in Ramah), the ancient and the Manner houſe, his father dwelt there before him, 1. Sam. 1;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.19.</note> where alſo you may bee informed touching the towne. Whereas there were of Ramahs foure or fiue,<note place="margin">v. Adrichom, of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this was Ramah Zophim in Mount Ephraim, which bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes his name from the ſituation of it; it ſtood high, and the name importeth no leſſe. In this Ramah <hi>Samuel</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time liued as a Magiſtrate, and here hee is interred. For the ſolemnity of the Funerall, it is ſuch as argues Iſraels loue, and <hi>Samuels</hi> worth, they doe him all the honour that is poſſible. Firſt, (Iſrael) the firſt borne of men, the glory of the world comes to the Funeral, (all Iſrael) all at once in the ſame place; they come from far, they come vpon the wings of the wind, they come (to lament) al mourners they come (to burie him) to bury him in his owne towne, (at his owne houſe); what can be done more in <hi>Samuels</hi> honour? To bee buried is an honour, buried in ones owne countrey much, in his owne place more; but to bee ſo buried as <hi>Samuel</hi> was, in ſuch a place, by ſuch a people, with ſo many teares, ſo great a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, this is <hi>Samuels</hi> happineſſe, and the Saints honour. You ſee then our third doctrine.</p>
            <p>An holy and profitable life ends in an happy and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable death: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> life is deaths ſeeds-time, death lifes harueſt; as here we ſowe, ſo there we reape; as here we ſet, ſo there we gather, of holineſſe, happineſſe, and of a bleſſed life, a death as bliſ-full. He that ſpends himſelfe vpon God and man, ſhal at the laſt haue all the honour that heauen and earth can
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3977:15"/>caſt vpon him. So <hi>Samuel</hi> found it, ſo <hi>Iacob,</hi> few men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to him in holineſſe, as few ſo honourably buried. So <hi>Aſa,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.14.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiah, Ioſiah, Dauid.</hi> &amp;c: but eſpecially for <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> thoſe great reformers, thoſe profitable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, the text takes ſpeciall notice of their obſequies. <hi>Ioſiah</hi> hauing receiued his deaths wound abroad, is brought home in his chariot,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.29.</note> and much honour attends him to his graue; he is buried amongſt his fathers and friends; all Ieruſalem, nay all Iudah, and the neighbouring townes are mourners; nay not profeſſors onely, but Preachers too, as <hi>Ieremy</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Theſe ſo mourned, as that their lamentation grew into a prouer be, Zach. 12. God and man concurred in this, that <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> name ſhould neuer die.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.33.</note> And as for <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> the holy Ghoſt points vs to his life and death; in his life time he was of greateſt vſe for Church and Common-weale, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he died, Iſrael ſlockes to the buriall; and where is he buried? in the chiefeſt Sepulcher of <hi>Davids</hi> ſonnes, and how? with greateſt honour; all Iſrael (ſaith the text), and Iudah too met together to doe him honour at his death, 2. Chron. 32.33. He ſtudied their good in life, they his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at his death: thus a profitable life reſignes to an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable death: thus are they honoured of all that minde. Gods glory, and the common good. A matter of leſſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> if we conſider three things: Firſt, that God hath vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken taken it ſhall be ſo, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2 30.</note> They that honour me ſhall be honoured by me, ſaith truth and honour it ſelfe: and in the hands of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> wiſedome is honour, as well as wealth, Prou. 3. Secondly, all matter of diſgrace is remoued by death, life and ſinne in the godly die together: when God diuides the ſoule from the body, he ſeparates ſinne from both; ſinne for the puniſhment he will not ſmite; ſinne for the ſtaine, that ſhall not blemiſh. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, he ſwayes the hearts of men to thoughts of mercy towards his, when once departed; hauing firſt couered their ſinnes himſelfe, he wipes the remembrance of them out of the heart of men, and preſents them with a daily view of grace and vertue. Thus <hi>Samuel</hi> that was ſo much quarrelled in his life, is as much honoured in his death; when hee dies, mans en<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e dies, his owne corruption dies: God will ſee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3977:15"/>none iniquity in <hi>Samuel,</hi> men after God ſhall doe the like.</p>
            <p>And is this ſo? then here we ſee what courſe muſt bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> if we will arriue at honour; men may dreame to meete with honour in many pathes; they may thinke to make their name by other meanes: but when they haue tyred themſelues in ſeeking this in by-paths, as the young ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents <hi>Elyahs</hi> body, they muſt with them ſeeke in heauen,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 2.16.</note> if euer they will finde. All honour comes from aboue, and there reſts where the God of honour places it; ſo that hee muſt be wonne by a godly life, before that honour can bee obtained. Beleeue it (brethren) nothing mends the name, but what mendes the ſoule; <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> may haue wealth, <hi>Achitophel</hi> wit, <hi>Herod</hi> ſpeech, <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bna</hi> a tombe, <hi>Ahab</hi> all, and yet be baſe and contemptible. <hi>Doeg</hi> may fawne, <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trephes</hi> climbe, <hi>Iezabel</hi> paint, <hi>Abſalom</hi> plot, and yet leaue their name as a curſe: theſe, theſe things that grow out of the dunghill, or duſt, will neuer build a name of honour, becauſe they will neuer worke any life of grace. The onely way to honour is through vertue, in the Heathens iudgement; a ſpeech as true as truth it ſelfe, if we vnderſtand it of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, not of morall vertues, but of ſauing grace. A godly fruitfull life, hath a fairer proſpect towards honour, then all the aduantages in the world beſides. Be one as poore as <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſimus,</hi> yet if <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> that is, profitable, his name out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues him: be one as great as King <hi>Iehoram,</hi> or <hi>Iehoiachim,</hi> if he idle out his life, he dies vndeſired, he liues vnlamented. In the ſecond of Chron. 24,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.</note> we haue two notable inſtances in one Chapter, to this purpoſe; the men are <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> and <hi>Iehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> the difference much betwixt them; the one was a king, the other a ſubiect: in life this ods, the one was truly profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and godly, the other contrary; in death therefore thus they are differenced, <hi>Iehoiadah</hi> waxed old, the other was rotten before tipe: next, <hi>Ichoiadah</hi> died naturally, the other by a violent hand: <hi>Ichoiadah</hi> in the loue of all, the other in the hatred of his owne men: <hi>Ichoiadah</hi> buried amongſt the kings; the other denied that honour; the reaſon? <hi>Ic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiadah</hi> (ſaith the text) had done good in Iſrael and towards God and his houſe, <hi>Ioaſh</hi> neither: what is the inference? ſurely this, the memoriall of the righteous is bleſſed, the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3977:16"/>name of the godly ſhall remaine for euer. God hath allowed both the good and the bad their portion;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou</hi> 10.</note> the righteous hath a double bleſſing, the wicked a double curſe vpon his name. The bleſſings are theſe; the name of the righteous is bleſſed, his memoriall precious, his name a perfume: ſecondly, his remembrance is for euer, Pſalm. 112. The curſes theſe, the name of the wicked rots, it quickly comes to nothing; whileſt it laſts it ſtinkes like carrion, and at laſt is left as a curſe behind him, as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith. What we heare ſpoken, we ſee executed in all ages. Conſult with your owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and tell me whether the names of Idolaters, drunkards, adulterers, ſwaggerers, be not rotten and accurſed; in deſpite of all titles, offices, policies, fauours whatſoeuer: when in the meane the righteous (notwithſtanding all ſlanders, cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, imputations, and aſperſions) is of bleſſed name and memorie; and if ſo, feede vpon the wind no longer, build Babels no more, lay no more foundations in hell, whileſt you thinke to erect a building by flattery, baſeneſſe, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancie, lying, ſwaggering, &amp;c: but goe to the Lord of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for laſting honour; pray much, reade much, heare much; honour him in all the paſſages of his worſhip, and you haue his word for your preferment: and as for men, bee to them as <hi>Iehoiadah</hi> was, profitable, and they ſhall bee to you as Iſrael to him, mercifull. Ah the fruitfull liuer findes mercy in his death, his conſcience fauours him, and hartens him vpon death it ſelfe: the Angels of God (thoſe officers of heauen) comfort him and fetch him in all ſtate to his crowne, the Lord of glory receiues him with all honour, and puts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the glory of heauen the Saints departed regard him as a part of themſelues, of Chriſt; the Saints liuing honour his name, and follow him to heauen, with their loues and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: the wicked haue a word of commendations for him, and the blind <hi>Balaam</hi> can ſay, O that my end might be like his!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.</note> thus honour and happineſſe (and nothing elſe) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide vs hereafter, if now we can lay forth our ſelues to God and mans aduantage. But for the wicked who beſtow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the world like drones in the hiue, who either haue no calling, or doe no ſeruice, and towards God ſo demeane
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3977:16"/>themſelues, as if they were his betters; ſcorning his children, ſcoffing at his Word, trampling vpon his Name, his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, his Worſhip; let them neuer deceiue themſelues, their names ſhall rot, they ſhall find no fauour in death, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſhall brawle them out of all quiet: men ſhall riſle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hues; their whoredomes, treacheries, villanies ſhall flie through the world; euery drunkard ſhall ſit vpon them; euery rake-hell iudge them, cenſure them, libell them. In the meane, whileſt that the name is thus torne below, the ſoule is brought before the Iudge, conuicted, committed to hell; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with ſhame, deliuered vp to euerlaſting contempt. O then be not curſed, but bleſſed, be happy, be honoured, bee well thought of in life, well ſpoken of after death; be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, be humble, be ſeruiceable; this is the way as heauen tells vs; a <hi>Samuels</hi> life will draw on a <hi>Samuels</hi> death, nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>In a ſecond place, let this afford a double comfort to fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> members, and faithfull Chriſtians: Firſt, for themſelues, let them know that the world will change ere long; the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, who haue now the applauſe, muſt downe; the godly, who as yet are vnder ſhame, ſhall ſhine.<note place="margin">Franzius in his hiſtor. Sacra.</note> The wicked (as one ſpeakes) are like hawkes, of great eſteeme whileſt liuing, but after nothing worth: the godly (on the other ſide) are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to tamer fowle, which are huſht forth, and little heeded whileſt liuing; but after death are brought into the Parlor. Semblably in the dayes of life, impietie hath the hand: after death the difference is as much betweene <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Samuel, Ioaſh</hi> and <hi>Iehoidah,</hi> as betwixt the Faulcon and Capon, Hauke and Hen. Yeeld then (beloued) to the worlds ſonnes; let them haue the place, giue them leaue to ſpeake; the time will come when honour ſhall know its home, and innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie haue its crowne: all the wiles in the world ſhall not keepe the wicked from contempt; nor all the wits in hell the godly from honour. <hi>Samuels</hi> name may be ouer-caſt and clouded for a time, but in the end his light will ſhew it ſelfe. Whileſt he is preſent, hee is not valued, his ſonnes were naught, his place meane, his gouernment vile: but this is <hi>Samuels</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, when gone, he is miſt; when dead, he is lamented; all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3977:17"/>ſtriues to doe him all honour; bleſſed bee that life that ends in ſo glorious a death; thrice happie that man, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God and all men do ſtriue to honor. Next for the godly friends, they haue wherin to comſort themſelues, for as much a holy life empties if ſelfe into an honourable death. A true Chriſtian may trauell in life vnder troubles and contempts: but marke his end, and you ſhall find (as peace, ſo) honour. When he is buried, a true and honourable funerall is ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized: euen mourne not in the face, but in the heart; reſpect him not in ſhew, but in truth; their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences reuerence him, their ſoules find a miſſe of him: the Angels of heauen man him in a goodly traine to heauen, the Saints on earth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him with greateſt affections to his graue: ſeuen, nay thrice ſeuen yeeres after the funerall he is not forgotten. Thus are the men whom the great King loues honoured: if any of ours haue performed ſuch a life, that he hath attained to ſuch a death, there is no place for repining. If God ſlay <hi>Aarons</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10.</note> he muſt be ſilent: If he honour ours, ſhall we mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur? What, ſhall <hi>Bethuel</hi> part with a daughter; <hi>Laban</hi> with a fiſter for an <hi>Iſacks</hi> ſake? Shall <hi>Barzill<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i</hi> in his age part with his ſtaffe, <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.</note> his ſonne, when he is to liue in <hi>Dauids</hi> Court? Shall men and women beare with patience the abſence of deareſt friends, when it is for their outward preferment; and when Chriſt would marry a child, preferre a friend, aduance our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, ſhould wee ſtand off? No: if this bee the worſt that death can doe to the godly, to ſtrip him of his raggs, and clothe him with robes; to free him from all contempts, and poſſeſſe him of greateſt honours; to redeeme him from all ſhame, and to crowne him with glorie in the harts, mouthes, conſciences of men, in the face of heauen and earth: lets ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer frowne vpon friends departure, but rather ſee (if poſſible) the meſſenger of this good ridings, and bleſſe the Lord for our adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tsin theirs. Indeed (beloued) we weep too faſt, when teares denie fight of mercies: in the death of <hi>Samuel</hi> there is game to him, as well as loſſe to vs, both ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. I know many preſent ſenſible of the one, I ſhall be wrongfull to conceale the other. Truth it is, there is fallen a great man in Iſrael: But how fallen? like <hi>Abner</hi> vpon a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3977:17"/>hand? or died he like a foole? Was he vnſenſible of his eſtate? Were his hands, his mouth, his heart tied? Was his end without honour? No brethren, he died in a full and ripe age, when the Lord had made the moſt of his life; he died in peace, he died with hopes of life in his heart, with words of grace in his lipps, and his Sunne did ſet in the higheſt point,<note place="margin">Vt eſſe Phaebi dulcius lumen ſolet iam tam cadentis.</note> in greateſt brightneſſe: time, place, manner, company, men, Angels, God, and all conſpired together to doe him all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in his death. Bleſſe the God of all ſpirits for this, all ye that are intereſſed in the ſame profeſſion and religion. Bleſſe the Lord for this, that hee ſo died, in ſuch a place, in ſuch a time, in ſuch a ſort, as the diuell hath receiued a foile, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion grace and honour by it. And thus Iſrael hath done his part in mourning, in burying <hi>Samuel</hi> at his houſe in Ramah.</p>
            <p>Now where is <hi>Dauid?</hi> ſoone after <hi>Samuels</hi> death, you find him in the Wilderneſſe of Paran; and this clauſe is like a corner ſtone, of double vſe, it cloſes one courſe and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth another. This Paran was a Wilderneſſe, vaſt and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, mountenous and rockie, hither <hi>Dauid</hi> eft ſoones repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when by <hi>Saul</hi> he was perſecuted: But why at this time? truely now hee hath fewer friends then before. <hi>Samuel</hi> hee much vſed before, as the ſtorie ſheweth vs: but now <hi>Samuel</hi> is gone. Now againe hee hath more enemies then before; <hi>Saul</hi> will be more bitter, falſe friends will bee true enemies: yea now Ramahs refuge (perhaps) will yeeld perſecutours, and <hi>Samuels</hi> ſonnes as like to hurt as harbour him; ſo that it is time for <hi>Dauid</hi> to flie. I ſhould doe you the greateſt wrong to purſue my meditations at large, giue me leaue to mind you of my thoughts, and I will fauour your patience. What a ſhame is it for Iſrael, for Ramah, for <hi>Samuels</hi> houſe, that when the Old man is gone, <hi>Dauid</hi> dare ſtay no longer amongſt them? O what a ſhamefull change is this! what a blemiſh to <hi>Samuels</hi> ſucceſſors, to all the Countrie! you that be in Iſrael ſuruiuing <hi>Samuel,</hi> take vnto you the heart, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, courage of <hi>Samuel;</hi> when perſecuted <hi>Dauid</hi> comes vnto you for ſuccour, driue him not into the Wilderneſſe; and let the friends of <hi>Samuel</hi> continue the life of <hi>Samuel</hi> in their houſes and behauiours. Ramah was a Citie of refuge for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3977:18"/>ſtreſſed perſons, an habitation for the Leuites, a Colledge for the Prophets, thither <hi>Dauid</hi> was euer welcome; for <hi>Dauid</hi> to be thruſt out by <hi>Doeg,</hi> to be courſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ramah into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of Paran, is ſuch a blemiſh to the place as can neuer be waſhed out. But why (to goe on) feares <hi>Dauid</hi> more now then before? good reaſon, <hi>Saul</hi> and all like <hi>Saul</hi> will now ſhew themſelues, and turne the inſide outward. <hi>Samuels</hi> death is twice mentioned, and either time a ſhrewd pranke of <hi>Sauls:</hi> firſt, hee perſecutes <hi>Dauid,</hi> as here: ſecondly, hee runnes to Witches, 1. Sam. 28.3, 7. In <hi>Samuels</hi> life-time Witches went downe: but when <hi>Samuel</hi> was dead, <hi>Saul</hi> can reliſh ſorcerie well enough. Thus the thoughts of many hearts will be diſcouered vpon a <hi>Samuels</hi> death; let <hi>Iehoiadah</hi> be buried, and <hi>Ioaſh</hi> will come to his bent againe. Let <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> head be once laid, good men, wife men, a fathers friends will be neglected; greene heads, worthleſſe perſons ſhall bee entertained: <hi>Rehoboam</hi> would not haue done ſo in <hi>Salomons</hi> dayes; but he is dead. Looke to it, looke to it (my brethren) all yee that haue profeſſed loue, zeale, religion in <hi>Samuels</hi> daies, that now you ſhew not <hi>Sauls</hi> ſpirit; be ſetled, be reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſtill for God, for the Word, for profeſſion, ſith the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and the promiſe, and the promiſer, and heauen promiſed ſtands as they did. If now any of you ſhall ſteale from God, and flie to the enemie; ſhal giue ouer his profeſſion, and turne perſecutor, ſcoffer,  hee proclaimes his owne hypocriſie: God from heauen proclaimes him a traitor, and will follow him with a <hi>crying conſcience, and reſtleſſe heart, till he hath laid him as low as hell.</hi> But whither flew <hi>Dauid?</hi> a poore refuge he hath yet ſome; though <hi>Samuel</hi> be dead, yet he hath a ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſuch as it is; <hi>Dauids</hi> life hangs not wholly vpon <hi>Samuels.</hi> The ſinners of Sion now opened vpon him, and followed him with full crie, Now his friend is gone, now his God is dead, now wee will bee vpon him,  Vpon him! fooliſh men, his God dead! <hi>Dauids</hi> God liues, though <hi>Samuel</hi> bee dead. His friend he hath loſt indeede, but not his father; hee muſt no more to Ramah, but in Paran there be rockes, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; in heauen there is a rocke that will neuer faile: bleſſed be the Lord for this comfort; when the diuel rores, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3977:18"/>rage, his <hi>Dauids</hi> are carried vpon wings into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, where they find a place. What ſhall I ſay more; <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> goeth to heauen, <hi>Dauid</hi> muſt abroad, both muſt from Ramah: ſee what death can doe, it maketh a diuorce betwixt deareſt friends. What of that? Therefore truſt not in friends, therefore dote not vpon friends; therefore call vpon friends whileſt preſent, and ſay, this child muſt ceaſe to be my child, this father to be my father,  we muſt be to one another, as if we had neuer been with one another; and therefore thinke of a departure. Therefore (in the ſecond place) make ſure Gods loue, get him to be thy friend, and that friendſhip is impregnable. Children thou maiſt looſe, and wife, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and friends; death can ſweepe away theſe: but thy God thou canſt neuer looſe, if once at league with him; come what will come, he will be euer for thee, euer with thee; if in priſon, he will be there; if in exile, there; if in the ſeas, there; where thou art with prayers, he will be with comſorts. And therfore if a ſeruant, get this Maſter; if a child, this Father; if a widow, this Husband; and then though all friends die, yet thou ſhalt liue ſo long as the heauens laſt, and Chriſt Ieſus liues; and liue in peace, and die in hope, and riſe with ioy, and reigne in glorie.</p>
            <p>Thus Iſrael and we haue brought two <hi>Samuels</hi> (theirs and ours) to their lodging; both faithfull in their places, honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their deaths; both ſo neare in agreement, that in the ſtorie of the one, you may reade the life of the other. My Text here ends it ſelfe, and proceedes no lower into a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular commendation of <hi>Samuel;</hi> and therefore if I follow my Text, rather then the times, it will not be offenſiue. Indeede <hi>Samuel</hi> is like to ſuch fruit as is ripe, and good when it is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, yet better if it lie a while: let him haue a time of mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, now hee is gathered; and his owne worth and our want, will ſet lum farre beyond all verball praiſes. In the meane, lets turne our ſelues from praiſing man, to praiſe that God, to whom the praiſe of all that is praiſe-worthie is only due, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3977:19"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Poſtſer.</note> I Was requeſted to enlarge and refine theſe points, but I find ſo much written of theſe arguments alreadie, that were is not more to ſatisfie others then my ſelfe, thou ſhouldeſt not (Reader) haue been troubled thus long. If thou canſt get any thing by theſe broken notes as they be, do; if God euer make mee able to doe thee a better turne in any other kind, I will. In the meane, the bleſſing of God be vpon vs and our Church.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
